<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>Brian Ketelsen</title>
        <link>undefined</link>
        <description>Brian Ketelsen - Blog</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Thu, 25 May 2023 01:05:17 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <image>
            <title>Brian Ketelsen</title>
            <url>undefined/favicon.ico</url>
            <link>undefined</link>
        </image>
        <copyright>All rights reserved 2023</copyright>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Being Black in Jiu-Jitsu]]></title>
            <link>undefined/articles/being-black-jiujitsu</link>
            <guid>undefined/articles/being-black-jiujitsu</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 23 May 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Encouraging a community of people that this martial art is perfect for us to be better and survive in this world that we live in.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<hr/><p>Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu (BJJ) is a dynamic martial art that has been gaining significant traction in the global arena. It&#x27;s deeply rooted in Brazil but has been quickly spreading to every corner of the world, sprouting academies everywhere. Yet, despite its far-reaching appeal, there&#x27;s been a certain level of hesitation amongst individuals from the black community to dive into BJJ, particularly if they find themselves as minority members in a majority white school. In this piece, we will dive into why it is crucial for more individuals from the black community to participate in BJJ, even in majority white schools, and offer some advice on navigating potential social barriers.</p><h2>The Appeal of BJJ</h2><p>At the core of it, BJJ is an incredibly rewarding sport that holistically develops both mind and body. It&#x27;s an art of grappling that not only instills a sense of self-defense but also imparts lessons on strength, flexibility, endurance, and mental resilience. It&#x27;s also been observed to have a positive effect on mental health, acting as a stress buster and anxiety reducer, while enhancing self-esteem and general wellbeing. Given these numerous advantages, it&#x27;s no surprise that a large number of people have passionately taken up the practice.</p><h2>The Challenge</h2><p>However, the prospect of joining a BJJ school as part of a racial minority can seem daunting for many from the black community. Although the BJJ community generally champions openness and acceptance, there are moments of ignorance and insensitivity toward people of color. This, however, should not dissuade black individuals from embracing BJJ. By being part of this community, you&#x27;re not just joining a group that fosters camaraderie, discipline, and respect but you&#x27;re also pushing boundaries and breaking stereotypes.</p><h2>Overcoming Obstacles</h2><p>One crucial aspect to remember when joining a BJJ school is the right to voice your boundaries and hold others accountable for their actions. Clear and open communication with your training partners and instructors about your expectations is key. Stand firm on your boundaries, but don&#x27;t hesitate to speak out when you feel disrespected or uncomfortable. Remember, though, that these conversations need to be approached with an open mind and willingness to educate others. Sharing your personal experiences and perspectives can be a powerful tool in creating a more inclusive and respectful environment.</p><h2>Tips for Navigating BJJ as a Minority</h2><ol><li><strong>Be clear and concise:</strong> When communicating your feelings and expectations, be direct and transparent. Use &quot;I&quot; statements to articulate your thoughts and avoid making assumptions about others&#x27; intentions.</li><li><strong>Educate others:</strong> If you encounter insensitive comments or behavior, use it as an opportunity to educate that individual about why such actions are unacceptable. Be patient and understanding, but do not hesitate to engage in these challenging conversations.</li><li><strong>Seek support:</strong> Cultivate a network of allies who understand and respect your boundaries. This can be other trainees, friends, or family members. Having a solid support system in place makes it easier to navigate difficult situations and can provide a sense of safety.</li><li><strong>Focus on your journey:</strong> Remember that your BJJ journey is about your personal growth and not about becoming a spokesperson for the entire black community. While it is important to stand up for yourself and others, don&#x27;t let others&#x27; ignorance divert you from your goals.</li></ol>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>me@brian.dev (Brian Ketelsen)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[What is Jiu-Jitsu]]></title>
            <link>undefined/articles/what-is-jiu-jitsu</link>
            <guid>undefined/articles/what-is-jiu-jitsu</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 23 May 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[What is Jiu-Jitsu]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<hr/><h1>What is Jiu-jitsu</h1><p>Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu (BJJ) is a martial art that originated in Brazil in the early 20th century. The art was developed by the Gracie family, who were known for their mastery of Japanese Jiu-Jitsu. The Gracies adapted the traditional art to suit their own style and preferences, and Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu was born.</p><p>BJJ is a grappling-based martial art that emphasizes technique, leverage, and submissions. Unlike other martial arts that rely on striking, BJJ focuses on ground fighting and submissions, making it an effective self-defense system for individuals of all sizes and strengths.</p><p>One of the unique features of BJJ is that it is often referred to as the &quot;gentle art.&quot; This term reflects the non-aggressive, non-violent nature of the art, as well as the emphasis on technique and leverage over brute strength. The philosophy behind the gentle art is that a smaller, weaker person can successfully defend themselves against a larger, stronger attacker by using proper technique and leverage.</p><p>In my opinion, the gentle art of Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu is not just about physical self-defense. It&#x27;s also about defending, strengthening, and protecting your personal boundaries. By training in BJJ, you learn to be accountable for your actions and to respect the boundaries of others. You also learn to assert your own boundaries and to protect your own peace.</p><p>BJJ is a sport that requires a balance of respect and selfishness. On one hand, you must respect your training partners and opponents, treating them with dignity and kindness. On the other hand, you must be selfish enough to protect your own personal boundaries and physical safety.</p><p>In BJJ, there is a collision of personal boundaries as practitioners grapple and struggle for control. However, this collision is not about aggression or violence. Instead, it is about mutual respect and the pursuit of excellence. By learning to navigate this collision with respect and accountability, BJJ practitioners develop not only physical strength and skill, but also mental and emotional fortitude.</p><p>In conclusion, Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu is a fascinating martial art that emphasizes technique, leverage, and the gentle art of self-defense. It is a sport that requires accountability and respect, as well as a balance of selfishness and selflessness. By practicing BJJ, individuals can not only protect themselves physically, but also develop a deeper sense of personal strength and peace.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>me@brian.dev (Brian Ketelsen)</author>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>